## Simon Azariah

Expert in Health/Social Systems, Management, PPP, Governance & HIV/AIDS

dr.simonazariah@gmail.com

## Summary

Simon is a Health Systems Management and Governance Specialist with more than 24 years experience in South & Central Asia and growing experience in Africa. Being a medical doctor with a Master's degree in Health Management, Planning & Policy and an MBA, he is especially well accepted to work with Governments at a senior/advisory level in developing countries. Simon has extensive experience of Policy, Strategic Planning, Systems Strengthening, Reforms, Evaluation and Surveillance, both in the broader health sector and HIV/AIDS. He is experienced in project design and management and is an expert in developing strategies to optimize health and social sectors' performance and enhance value for money. He comes with extensive experience of working with the government and non-government sectors.

#### Specialties:

- Systems Development and Institutional Strengthening
- Policy, Planning & Programming, Management & Leadership: health and social sectors
- Governance, Public-Private Partnership
- Organizational and Project Management
- Appraisals, Monitoring, Evaluation
- HIV/AIDS and Harm Reduction

## Experience

# Specialist: Health Systems, Health Management, PPPs, Health Governance, HIV/AIDS at Self Employed

April 2012 - Present (1 year 4 months)

- » # Health & Governance Specialist: Design of UNFPA Pakistan's Demand Side Financing Voucher System for FP services. Contracted by Options UK. (Apr Jun 2013)
- » # Strategic Planning Specialist: Developing Multi-Sectoral Nutrition Strategy for all four provinces of Pakistan for Government, Private Sector and Development Partners. Contracted by WHO Pakistan. (Apr 2013)
- » # Health Systems Specialist: Review & Strategizing PPAF's Health Programme in the Private Sector. Contracted by Pakistan Poverty Alleviation Fund for its USD 50 million Health Programme. (Mar – May 2013)
- » # Team Leader: Annual Review of Enhancing Nigeria's Response to HIV/AIDS a DFID funded GBP 118m project. Contracted by DFID Nigeria. (Jan Feb 2013)
- » # Health Governance and PPP Specialist (Pakistan) with Options Consulting UK for DFID funded Reproductive Health Franchise Project contracted to MSI, Pop Council and Option Consulting UK (Call down contracted Aug 12 Jul 2016)
- » # Health lead for ICAI (International Commission for Aid Impact) of the UK Parliament for review of

DFID Pakistan's effectiveness of UK Aid investments in Pakistan through KPMG-UK & Agulhas-UK. (Apr – Dec 12)

- » # HIV/AIDS and Management Specialist (Central Asia) contracted by HLSP UK for end of project evaluation of DFID funded Central Asia Regional HIV-AIDS Programme (Sep Nov 2012)
- » # Management Consultant for World Bank (Pakistan). Assisting the World Bank to undertake policy advocacy and adoption of Nutrition Strategy at the devolved Provincial Departments of Health in Pakistan (Jun Oct 12)
- » # Health Systems Specialist for Mid-term Evaluation of CIDA funded CAD \$25 million Capacity Building and Access to Medicines, Afghanistan project of Health Partners International Canada being implemented within MoPH Afghanistan through Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd. (Apr May 12)

# Country Director [Pakistan], CIDA: HIV/AIDS Surveillance Project at Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd.

January 2009 - March 2012 (3 years 3 months)

Planned, managed and delivered in partnership with and through the National and Provincial AIDS Control Programs of Government of Pakistan:

- National round of HIV Integrated Behavioural and Biological Surveillance among MARPs in 20 cities 24000 samples
- National HIV Surveillance among ANC clients in 9 districts 27000 samples
- HIV Surveillance among Mine Workers in Balochistan 2200 samples
- National and Provincial HIV Data Coordination Units established

Contracted 19 Civil Society Organisations and HIV testing facilities, 150+ short term field personnel and consultants for data collection, training, data processing and report writing

1 recommendation available upon request

# CONSULTANCIES as Health Systems/Governance, Management, HIV/AIDS Specialist at Independent Consulting

1999 - 2011 (12 years)

- Annual Review of DFID (3-country) Central Asia Regional HIV/AIDS Program (Kyrgyzstan & Tajikistan components). HLSP-UK/DFID 2011
- Output to Purpose Review of DFID funded Enhanced Nigerian Response to HIV/AIDS. HLSP/DFID 2011
- Annual Review of Cambodia Country Program of AusAID funded HIV/AIDS Asia Regional (6 country) Program. HLSP-UK/AusAID through IDSS 2011
- Evaluation/Output to Purpose Review of Uzbekistan component of DFID funded (3-country) Central Asia Regional HIV/AIDS Program. HLSP-UK/DFID 2009
- Analytical review of government health sector in Bangladesh. Agriteam Canada 2009
- HIV-AIDS & Harm Reduction Specialist (Part of 4-member Team as). Appraisal of national Targeted Interventions for HIV Prevention in Bangladesh. HLSP-UK/DFID 2007
- Appraisal of DFID-funded Central Asia Regional HIV/AIDS Program as Harm Reduction Specialist in Tajikistan for GRM-UK - 2006
- Coordination of UN Regional Task Force on IDUs& HIV/AIDS for UNAIDS and UNODC Regional offices for Asia & Pacific based at Bangkok - 2006

- Health Systems Strengthening Consultant. Design of CIDA funded Systems-Oriented Health Investment Program for Pakistan. Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd. Canada 2005
- Medical relief for Tsunami victims: Led a multidisciplinary team of Doctors & Relief workers in Sri-Lanka; with Sri Lankan Ministry of Health Corporate Sector, Christian Council of Sri Lanka & SEDEC 2005
- Critical appraisal of interventions for youth in Govt & NGO sector in Pakistan & development of intellectual framework for Youth Development , Population Council 2001
- Establishing Information Resource Centres for Government District Health Systems & Centre in Punjab, DFID/The British Council 2000
- Project Manager Multiple Indicators Cluster Survey of Afghanistan 2000 of Eastern, UNICEF Afghanistan 2000
- Evaluation of UNFPA's 2 national projects: "Strengthening RH & Trg Program" AND "Family Health Training", MoPW as M&E Specialist 1999

# Project Director, CIDA: Systems-Oriented Health Investment Program at Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd.

March 2006 - September 2010 (4 years 7 months)

Worked in Advisory capacity to Punjab Government's Provincial Health Department for strengthening provincial and district health reforms

- District Health Systems strengthened: DHMTs formed, legislated and functioning in Punjab province, Pakistan
- District health planning and budgeting systems developed and installed
- Health Promotion Department established in Provincial Directorate of Health
- Gender Audit of Provincial and District Health Departments and Punjab Health Sector Reforms Program
- Cadre reform of largest paramedical cadre (Dispensers) in Punjab completed with new curriculum, textbook and training capacity

1 recommendation available upon request

# Project Director, DFID: HIV/AIDS Prevention with Drug Harm Reduction Project at Futures Group Europe

2002 - 2005 (3 years)

Technical and Governance assistance on Harm Reduction to Federal Ministry of Health and Federal Ministry of Narcotics Control

- Intersectoral Coordination established between National AIDS Control Program and Anti-Narcotics Force
- Pakistan's Harm Reduction model developed and established
- Capacity of government and NGOs built on Harm Reduction and HIV prevention services
- Harm Reduction Services established in all provincial headquarters in Pakistan through 9 NGO contracts based on PPP

1 recommendation available upon request

## Monitoring & Evaluation Specialist at UNICEF Afghanistan

March 2001 - April 2002 (1 year 2 months)

Worked in close coordination and partnership with Ministry of Public Health Afghanistan

- Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey of Afghanistan (2001) completed for South and East of Afghanistan

- Nutrition and Mortality Assessments in Badghis and Maslakh IDP camps completed (100,000+ population)
- BBC Afghanistan's monitoring capacity developed
- UNICEF Afghanistan's country report 2002

1 recommendation available upon request

### Project Coordinator, DFID: 2nd Family Heatlh Project at British Council

1997 - 2000 (3 years)

Technical Assistance to Punjab Provincial Health Department and Health Department of Metropolitan Corporation of Lahore

- Developed complete reform package and obtained legal approval for Lahore city's Urban health department
- Developed district decentralized health systems for four pilot districts in Punjab through a team of district coordinators
- Developed and trained Chief Executives of Autonomous Health Institutions and District Governments of Punjab
- Managed Technical Cooperation Training of DFID/British Government for health sector

### Honors and Awards

## **Distinction in MA (HMPP)**

The University of Leeds

September 1996

Awarded Distinction by The University of Leeds in MA Health Management, Planning & Policy degree.

# **Projects**

## **Contracting NGOs for HIV/AIDS**

July 2004 to July 2004

Members: Simon Azariah, Asma Bokhari, Altaf Sonia, Bruce M.

Lessons learnt on Public-Private Partnership/contracting NGO sector for service provision in HIV/AIDS & Harm Reduction area

## Systems approach to improvement of HIV/AIDS Prevention - HAARP Cambodia Annual Review 2011 April 2011 to April 2011

Members:Simon Azariah

Annual Review of Cambodia Country Program of HIV/AIDS Regional Program; looks at systemic issues and their impact on HIV/AIDS Program effectiveness and proposes structural and systemic changes to address the issues. Please go to: http://www.haarp-online.org/Publications.aspx and click on HAARP Cambodia Annual Review 2011 (6th in the list)

#### Produced first Pakistani telefilm on HIV/AIDS

January 2011 to January 2012

Members: Simon Azariah, CR Shanzer (Clarence Rufin) - producer, Amin Iqbal - writer and director

Conceptualized and produced Pakistan's first full length telefim on HIV/AIDS (called 'SHIFA'). The film was selected on merit and was telecast by Pakistan's largest and international TV Channel: GEO TV: www.harpalgeo.tv/details.asp?id=128

To see the film please visit (5 parts): vidpk.com/63900/Telefilm-Shifa-on-Geo-Tv-P-1/vidpk.com/63900/Telefilm-Shifa-on-Geo-Tv-P-2/vidpk.com/63900/Telefilm-Shifa-on-Geo-Tv-P-3/vidpk.com/63900/Telefilm-Shifa-on-Geo-Tv-P-4/vidpk.com/63900/Telefilm-Shifa-on-Geo-Tv-P-5/

### Courses

### **Independent Coursework**

Applied Epidemiology, The Aga Khan University - 1994

Scientific Foundations of Surgery, University of Edinburgh - 1991

# Languages

English(Native or bilingual proficiency)Urdu(Native or bilingual proficiency)Punjabi(Native or bilingual proficiency)French(Elementary proficiency)

**Hindi** (Limited working proficiency)

## Skills & Expertise

Health Systems Research Management Policy Analysis Strategic Planning Project Appraisal Decentralization Monitoring & Evaluation
Cross-functional Team Leadership
Health Sector Reforms
Program Management
Critical Thinking
Harm Reduction - HIV/AIDS
Proposal Writing
Health Care Systems

**Harm Reduction** 

**Public Health** 

**Program Evaluation** 

**NGOs** 

**Capacity Building** 

**Public/private Partnerships** 

**Civil Society** 

**Technical Assistance** 

**Human Rights** 

**Sustainable Development** 

**Health Promotion** 

**Health Policy** 

### Education

### **Premier College of Business Admin & Economics**

MBA, Business Management, Marketing Communications, 1997 - 1998

## Nuffield Institute for Health, University of Leeds

Master's degree, Health Management, Planning & Policy, 1995 - 1996

### **University of the Punjab**

MBBS, Medicine, 1983 - 1988

Activities and Societies: Patients Welfare Society

#### Forman Christian College, Lahore

FSc, Pre-Medicine/Pre-Medical Studies, 1980 - 1982

Grade: A

Activities and Societies: Junior Biology Association;

National Cadet Corps

### Interests

Factors influencing Public-Private Partnerships in resource constrained nations.

Community governance & empowerment.

360 degree analysis of social & development issues.

# Simon Azariah

Expert in Health/Social Systems, Management, PPP, Governance & HIV/AIDS

dr.simonazariah@gmail.com



# 4 people have recommended Simon

"With his primary responsibility field based management of the HIV/AIDS Surveillance Project, Simon proved himself to be excellent project manager. His approach was strategic which enabled the project team to deliver an ambitious workplan during a year of disruptive restructuring in Pakistan's health system. He also oversaw finances diligently and put in place transparent systems for procurement. I would recommend him for both health project management and health systems technical assistance roles."

— **Michelle Munro**, *Senior Health Specialist*, *Agriteam Canada*, managed Simon at Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd.

"Simon is a strategic, creative and multi-sectoral thinker, able to bring together knowledge of health services delivery, human resources management, business management, technology and communications. He is hard-working and results-oriented, with attention to detail and excellent client-management skills. I would not hesitate to recommend Simon for project management and advisory services related to health and HIV/AIDS."

— **Morag Humble**, *Canadian Project Manager*, *CIDA-SOHIP*, managed Simon at Agriteam Canada Consulting Ltd.: Systems-Oriented Health Investment Program

"Simon's diplomacy and persistence was the key factor in bringing the military-led Anti-Narcotics Force, which was extremely resistant to the idea of harm reduction, to the same table as the National AIDS Control Program. By devising comprehensive and transparent contracting processes he also managed to forge effective partnerships between the government and NGOs. His strong systems approach and active project management also helped to make the project outputs sustainable through the Enhanced HIV/AIDS Control Program of Pakistan. Both DFID and the government praised the project's contribution to HIV prevention among injecting drug users in Pakistan, which is a testament to Simon's strategic approach and his excellent planning and management skills."

- Bruce M., Director of Programmes, Futures Group Europe, managed Simon at Futures Group Europe

"Simon worked as a Monitoring and Evaluation Specialist for the Unicef Afghanistan country office from Apr 2001 to May 2002. I found Simon to be an extremely focused, organized and undeterred professional with outstanding leadership and management skills. Despite extremely difficult relationship with the then Taliban-led government, heightened security concerns due to ongoing armed conflict, difficult terrain and lack of infrastructure and human resources Simon did an excellent job in organizing a local team of 100+

surveyors, cartographers and logisticians and successfully completed MICS in three provinces. He also completed the morbidity and mortality assessments for women and children in huge IDP camps in Herat and built program monitoring capacity of BBC Afghanistan staff. His work in Afghanistan is a demonstration of his excellent communication, diplomatic and project management capabilities in addition to his advanced acumen in monitoring, planning and evaluation"

- Solofo Ramaroson, Senior Programme Officer, UNICEF, managed Simon at UNICEF Afghanistan

Contact Simon on LinkedIn